It was November 1, 2002,
كان 1 نوفمبر 2002
my first day as a principal,
أول يوم لي كمديرة،
but hardly my first day in the school district of Philadelphia.
ولكن للأسف أول يوم لي كان بمدرسة بمقاطعة فيلادلفيا
I graduated from Philadelphia public schools,
تخرجت من مدرسة عمومية بولاية فيلادلفيا،
and I went on to teach special education for 20 years
لأدرّس بالتعليم الخاص لمدة 20 سنة
in a low-income, low-performing school
بمدرسة ذات دخل وأداء منخفضين
in North Philadelphia,
بفيلادلفيا الشمالية،
where crime is rampant
حيث تفشي الجريمة
and deep poverty is among the highest in the nation.
و الفقر المدقع على مستوى البلاد.
Shortly after I walked into my new school,
بعد فترة قصيرة من التحاقي بالمدرسة الجديدة
a huge fight broke out among the girls.
نشب نزاع حاد بين الفتيات.
After things were quickly under control,
بعد أن تمت السيطرة على كل شيء،
I immediately called a meeting
طلبت القيام باجتماع فوري
in the school's auditorium
بقاعة الاجتماعات بالمدرسة
to introduce myself as the school's new principal.
لأعرّف بنفسي كمديرة جديدة للمدرسة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I walked in angry,
دخلت غاضبة،
a little nervous --
متوترة قليلا --
(Laughter) --
(ضحك) --
but I was determined
ولكنني كنت مصرّة
to set the tone for my new students.
على تعديل صوتي لمقابلة تلامذتي الجدد
I started listing as forcefully as I could
بدأت بكل ما أوتيت من قوّة بذكر
my expectations for their behavior
توقّعاتي بخصوص سلوكهم
and my expectations for what they would learn in school.
وما سيتعلمونه بالمدرسة.
When, all of a sudden,
ودون توقع
a girl way in the back of the auditorium,
تقف فتاة جالسة
she stood up
نهاية القاعة.
and she said, "Miss!
وتقول: "آنسة !
Miss!"
آنسة !"
When our eyes locked, she said,
وعندما اتجهت كل الأنظار إليها، قالت،
"Why do you keep calling this a school?
"لماذا أنت مصرّة على وصفها بالمدرسة؟
This is not a school."
هذه ليست مدرسة."
In one outburst,
في انفجار واحد،
Ashley had expressed what I felt
قالت آشلي ما شعرت به
and never quite was able to articulate
وعجز عنه الصامتون
about my own experience when I attended a low-performing school
حول تجربتي حينما التحقت بمدرسة هزيلة الأداء
in the same neighborhood, many, many, many years earlier.
في نفس المنطقة قبل الكثير و الكثير من السنوات
That school was definitely not a school.
تلك المدرسة لم تكن دون أدنى شك مدرسة
Fast forwarding a decade later to 2012,
وبعد عِقدٍ مضى بسرعة وحتى 2012،
I was entering my third low-performing school as principal.
كنت مديرة لثالث مدرسة هزيلة الأداء
I was to be Strawberry Mansion's fourth principal in four years.
وكنت المديرة الرابعة في أربع سنوات بمدرسة "ستراوبري مانشين"
It was labeled "low-performing and persistently dangerous"
والتي كانت تُصنّف "كمدرسة هزيلة الأداء ودائمة الخطر"
due to its low test scores
بسبب الدرجات المتدنية للاختبارات
and high number of weapons,
والانتشار الواسع للأسلحة،
drugs, assaults and arrests.
والمخدرات والاعتداءات والاعتقالات.
Shortly as I approached the door of my new school
باختصار عندما اقتربت من باب مدرستي الجديدة
and attempted to enter,
وهممت بالدخول،
and found the door locked with chains,
وجدت الباب مغلقا بالسلاسل،
I could hear Ashley's voice in my ears
عندها رن في أذني صوت آشلي
going, "Miss! Miss!
وهي تقول "آنستي! آنستي!
This is not a school."
هذه ليست مدرسة. "
The halls were dim and dark from poor lighting.
كانت الأروقة قاتمة ومظلمة بسبب سوء الإضاءة
There were tons of piles of broken old furniture
كان هناك أطنان من حطام الأثاث القديم
and desks in the classrooms,
والمكاتب بقاعات الدرس
and there were thousands of unused materials and resources.
كما كان هناك الآلاف من الأدوات والموارد غير المستعملة
This was not a school.
هذه لم تكن مدرسة.
As the year progressed,
ومع مرور السنة الدراسية،
I noticed that the classrooms were nearly empty.
لاحظت أن الفصول الدراسية كانت تقريبا فارغة.
The students were just scared:
كان التلامذة خائفون:
scared to sit in rows in fear that something would happen;
خائفون من الاصطفاف خوفا من حدوث خطب ما،
scared because they were often teased in the cafeteria for eating free food.
خائفون لأنهم كانوا يتعرضون للمضايقة عند تناولهم للطعام المجاني بالكافيتيريا.
They were scared from all the fighting and all the bullying.
كانوا خائفين من جميع أشكال النزاعات والتهديدات
This was not a school.
لم تكن هذه مدرسة.
And then, there were the teachers,
وكذلك كان هناك المدرسون،
who were incredibly afraid for their own safety,
كانوا خائفين بشكل لا يصدق على سلامتهم،
so they had low expectations for the students and themselves,
لذلك كانت توقعاتهم متدنية بالنسبة لهم ولتلامذتهم
and they were totally unaware of their role
وكانوا جاهلين بدورهم كليا
in the destruction of the school's culture.
في بناء ثقافة المدرسة.
This was the most troubling of all.
كانت هذه أكبر مشكلة.
You see, Ashley was right,
أترون، كانت آشلي محقة،
and not just about her school.
وليس فقط بالنسبة لمدرستها.
For far too many schools,
ولكن بالنسبة للعديد من المدارس،
for kids who live in poverty,
للأطفال الفقراء،
their schools are really not schools at all.
مدارسهم لم تكن حقا مدارس.
But this can change.
ولكن هذا يمكن أن يتغير.
Let me tell you how it's being done at Strawberry Mansion High School.
دعوني أخبركم كيف تم ذلك بالمدرسة الثانوية "ستراوبري مانشين".
Anybody who's ever worked with me will tell you
اسألوا أي شخص عمل معي وسوف يخبركم بذلك
I am known for my slogans.
فأنا معروفة بشعاراتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So today, I am going to use three
اذن اليوم، سوف أستعمل ثلاثة
that have been paramount in our quest for change.
أفضل شعارات والتي كانت سببا في سعينا نحو التغيير.
My first slogan is:
أول شعار لي هو:
if you're going to lead, lead.
إذا كنت ستقوم بالقيادة، فلتقم بذلك.
I always believed
لطالما آمنت
that what happens in a school and what does not happen in a school
كل ما يحدث في المدرسة أو لا يحدث
is up to the principal.
هو مسؤولية مدير المدرسة.
I am the principal,
أنا المديرة،
and having that title required me to lead.
والحصول على ذلك الّلقب يُحتّم عليّ القيادة.
I was not going to stay in my office,
لم أكن مستعدة للجلوس في مكتبي،
I was not going to delegate my work,
أو تفويض عملي لشخص آخر،
and I was not going to be afraid to address anything
ولم أكن أشعر بالخوف من منع أي شيء
that was not good for children,
لن يخدم مصلحة الأطفال،
whether that made me liked or not.
سواء أحبوني لذلك أم لا.
I am a leader,
أنا القائدة،
so I know I cannot do anything alone.
لذلك أنا واعية بعدم قدرتي على تسيير كل شيء بمفردي.
So, I assembled a top-notch leadership team
لذلك اخترت أحسن فريق للقيادة
who believed in the possibility of all the children,
والذي كان مُؤمنا بقدرة الأطفال،
and together, we tackled the small things,
ومعا بدأنا باستهداف المواضيع الصغيرة،
like resetting every single locker combination by hand
كتخصيص أقفال يديوية لكل شخص
so that every student could have a secure locker.
لكي يحصل كل تلميذ على قفل مُؤمّن.
We decorated every bulletin board in that building
قمنا بتزيين كل اللوحات في البناية
with bright, colorful, and positive messages.
برسائل إيجابية وتبعث البهجة في النفوس.
We took the chains off the front doors of the school.
أزلنا كل الأقفال من الأبواب الأمامية للمدرسة
We got the lightbulbs replaced,
غيرنا كل المصابيح،
and we cleaned every classroom to its core,
كما نظفنا كل قاعات الدروس،
recycling every, every textbook that was not needed,
وقمنا بإزالة كل كتاب نعم كل كتاب غير صالح للاستعمال
and discarded thousands of old materials and furniture.
واللآلاف من المواد والأثاث القديم.
We used two dumpsters per day.
استعملنا حاويتين من الحجم الكبير في كل يوم .
And, of course, of course,
وبالطبع، بالطبع،
we tackled the big stuff,
عالجنا المواضيع المهمة،
like rehauling the entire school budget
مثل إعادة سحب ميزانية المدرسة
so that we can reallocate funds to have more teachers and support staff.
لإعادة تخصيص المال لانتداب معلمين آخرين وفريق دعم.
We rebuilt the entire school day schedule from scratch
أعدنا برمجة الجدول الدراسي اليومي من الصفر
to add a variety of start and end times,
وذلك لإضافة المواضيع المتنوعة،
remediation, honors courses,
والمعالجة والمقررات الشرفية،
extracurricular activities, and counseling,
والنشاطات اللامدرسية والإرشاد،
all during the school day.
كل هذا خلال اليوم الدراسي
All during the school day.
كل هذا خلال اليوم الدراسي.
We created a deployment plan
وقمنا بتشكيل خطة انتشار
that specified where every single support person and police officer would be
والتي مكنتنا من تحديد مكان كل شخص مساعد وشرطي
every minute of the day,
خلال كل دقيقة من اليوم،
and we monitored at every second of the day,
وقمنا بالقيادة خلال كل ثانية من اليوم،
and, our best invention ever,
وأفضل اختراع لدينا،
we devised a schoolwide discipline program
ابتكارنا لبرنامج ضبط السلوك للمدرسة بأكملها
titled "Non-negotiables."
بعنوان '' غير قابل للنقاش ''
It was a behavior system --
كان نظاما للسلوك --
designed to promote positive behavior at all times.
مُخصصا لتعزيز السلوك الإيجابي في كل الأوقات.
The results?
النتيجة ؟
Strawberry Mansion was removed from the Persistently Dangerous List
تمت إزالة مدرسة ستراوبري مانشين من قائمة الخطر المستمر
our first year after being --
بعد سنة، بعد أن كانت
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)--
after being on the Persistently Dangerous List for five consecutive years.
بعد أن كانت في قائمة الخطر المستمر لمدة 5 أعوام متتالية.
Leaders make the impossible possible.
القادة يجعلون المستحيل ممكنا.
That brings me to my second slogan:
وهو ما يُحيلني إلى شعاري الثاني :
So what? Now what?
وإن يكن؟! أين المفر؟!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
When we looked at the data,
عندما نظرنا إلى البيانات،
and we met with the staff,
وتقابلنا مع فريق العمل،
there were many excuses
كان هناك الكثير من الأعذار
for why Strawberry Mansion was low-performing and persistently dangerous.
بخصوص الأداء المنخفض لستراوبري مانشين والخطر المستمّر الذي تشهده.
They said that only 68 percent of the kids come to school on a regular basis,
قيل بأن نسبة الأطفال الذين يلتحقون بالمدرسة بصفة منتظمة هي 68 بالمائة
100 percent of them live in poverty,
ونسبة مائة بالمائة منهم هم من الفقراء.
only one percent of the parents participate,
فقط واحد بالمائة من الأولياء يُشاركون
many of the children
الكثير من الأطفال
come from incarceration and single-parent homes,
يأتون من السجن ومن عائلات أُحادية الوالد،
39 percent of the students have special needs,
39 بالمائة من التلامذة لديهم احتياجات خاصة،
and the state data revealed
وكشفت بيانات الحالة
that six percent of the students were proficient in algebra,
بأن 6 بالمائة من التلامذة بارعون في الرياضيات،
and 10 were proficient in literature.
و10 بالمائة في الأدب.
After they got through telling us all the stories
بعد أن أخبرونا كل القصص
of how awful the conditions and the children were,
عن مدى سوء الظروف والأطفال،
I looked at them,
نظرت إليهم،
and I said, "So what. Now what?
وقلت، " وإن يكن؟! أين المفر؟!
What are we gonna do about it?"
ماذا سنفعل بخصوص هذا؟"
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Eliminating excuses at every turn became my primary responsibility.
أصبحت مسؤوليتي الأولى القضاء على الأعذار في كل منعطف.
We addressed every one of those excuses
قمنا بمعالجة كل عذر من هذه الأعذار
through a mandatory professional development,
من خلال التطوير المحترف الضروري،
paving the way for intense focus on teaching and learning.
لتعبيد الطريق للتركيز الحاد على التدريس والتعلَُم.
After many observations,
وبعد العديد من المتابعات،
what we determined was that teachers knew what to teach
تبيّن لنا أنّ المدرسين كانوا على معرفة بما سيدرّسونه
but they did not know how to teach
ولكن لم يعرفوا طريقة تدريس
so many children with so many vast abilities.
الكثير من الأطفال ذوي الكفاءات العالية.
So, we developed a lesson delivery model for instruction
لذلك، قمنا بتطوير نموذج للتدريس
that focused on small group instruction,
والذي يُركّز على تدريس المجموعات الصغيرة
making it possible for all the students to get their individual needs met
وهذا ما ممكّن كل التلامذة من الحصول على احتياجاتهم الفردية
in the classroom.
التي تنقصهم في الفصل الدراسي.
The results?
النتيجة ؟
After one year, state data revealed
بعد سنة، بيّنت بيانات الحالة
that our scores have grown by 171 percent in Algebra
أن النسبة المئوية شهدت ارتفاعا بمائة وواحد وسبعون بالمائة في الرياضيات
and 107 percent in literature.
ومائة وسبعة بالمائة في الأدب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We have a very long way to go,
مازال المشوار طويلا،
a very long way to go,
طويلا جدا،
but we now approach every obstacle with a "So What. Now What?" attitude.
ولكننا نواجه كل صعوبة تعترضنا بطريقة "وإن يكن؟! أين المفر؟!"
And that brings me to my third and final slogan.
وهو ما يُحيلني إلى شعاري الثالث والأخير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If nobody told you they loved you today,
إذا لم يُخبرك أحد بأنه يُحبك اليوم،
you remember I do, and I always will.
فتذكر بأنني أحبك وسأظل أحبك.
My students have problems:
يُواجه طلابي مجموعة من المشاكل:
social, emotional and economic problems
مشاكل إجتماعية وعاطفية واقتصادية
you could never imagine.
لم تخطر على بالك قطّ.
Some of them are parents themselves,
البعض منهم هم أولياء،
and some are completely alone.
والبعض الآخر بمفردهم.
If someone asked me my real secret
إذا سألني أحدهم عن سري الحقيقي
for how I truly keep Strawberry Mansion moving forward,
وراء المضي قدما بستراوبري مانشين،
I would have to say that I love my students
سوف أجيب بأنني أحب تلامذتي
and I believe in their possibilities
وأؤمن بإمكانياتهم
unconditionally.
بدون شروط.
When I look at them,
عندما أنظر اليهم،
I can only see what they can become,
أرى فقط مالذي يُمكنهم ان يُصبحوا عليه،
and that is because I am one of them.
وذلك لأنني واحدة منهم،
I grew up poor in North Philadelphia too.
أنا عشت فقيرة بفيلادلفيا الشمالية أيضا.
I know what it feels like to go to a school that's not a school.
أعرف شعور الالتحاق بمدرسة ليست بمدرسة.
I know what it feels like to wonder
أعرف شعور أن تتساءل
if there's ever going to be any way out of poverty.
هل يوجد حتما طريق للخروج من هذا الفقر.
But because of my amazing mother,
ولكن بفضل والدتي الرائعة،
I got the ability to dream
كان من الممكن أن أحلم
despite the poverty that surrounded me.
بالرغم من الفقر الذي كان يُحيط بي.
So --
اذن --
(Applause) --
(تصفيق) --
if I'm going to push my students
إذا كنت سأقوم بتشجيع طلبتي
toward their dream and their purpose in life,
لتحقيق أحلامهم وسبب وجودهم في الحياة،
I've got to get to know who they are.
فينبغي حتما ان أعرف من هم.
So I have to spend time with them,
لذلك يجب أن أقضي وقتا معهم،
so I manage the lunchroom every day.
فقمت بالإشراف اليومي في المطعم المدرسي .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And while I'm there,
وبينما كنت هناك،
I talk to them about deeply personal things,
كنت أتحدث معهم حول مواضيع شخصية جدا
and when it's their birthday,
وعندما يكون هناك عيد ميلاد أحدهم،
I sing "Happy Birthday"
أغني له أغنية الميلاد"عيد ميلاد سعيد"
even though I cannot sing at all.
بالرغم من أنني لا أجيد الغناء بتاتا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I often ask them,
أسألهم دائما،
"Why do you want me to sing when I cannot sing at all?"
"لماذا تطلبون مني أن أغني وأنا لا أجيد ذلك بتاتا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they respond by saying,
ويُجيبون
"Because we like feeling special."
" لأننا نحب أن نشعر بأننا مُميّزون "
We hold monthly town hall meetings
نقوم كل شهر باجتماعات مفتوحة
to listen to their concerns,
للاستماع إلى اهتماماتهم،
to find out what is on their minds.
لمعرفة ما يجول في رؤوسهم.
They ask us questions like, "Why do we have to follow rules?"
يطرحون أسئلة مثل، " لماذا يجب علينا اتباع القواعد؟ "
"Why are there so many consequences?"
" لماذا ينجر عن ذلك العديد من النتائج؟"
"Why can't we just do what we want to do?"
" لماذا لا نقوم بما نُريد القيام به؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They ask, and I answer each question honestly,
هم يسألون وانا أجيب عن كل سؤال بصراحة،
and this exchange in listening helps to clear up any misconceptions.
وهذا التبادل في الاستماع سيُساعد على إزالة أي سوء فهم
Every moment is a teachable moment.
كل لحظة هي لحظة ممكن التعلم أثناءها
My reward,
مكافأتي،
my reward
مكافأتي
for being non-negotiable in my rules and consequences
لكوني لا أسمح بمناقشة قواعدي ونتائج ذلك
is their earned respect.
هو اكتساب احترامهم.
I insist on it,
أنا أُصرّ على ذلك،
and because of this, we can accomplish things together.
وبفضل ذلك نستطيع أن ننجز الأشياء معا.
They are clear about my expectations for them,
أنا واضحة بخصوص توقّعاتي لهم،
and I repeat those expectations every day over the P.A. system.
وأُعيد ذكر هذه التوقّعات كلّ يوم عبر مكبر صوت الجمهور.
I remind them --
أُذكّرهم --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I remind them of those core values
أذكّرهم بهذه القيم الأساسية بخصوص
of focus, tradition, excellence,
التركيز والتقاليد والامتياز
integrity and perseverance,
الإخلاص والمثابرة،
and I remind them every day
وأُذكّرهم كلّ يوم
how education can truly change their lives.
بمدى أهميّة التعليم في تغيير حياتهم.
And I end every announcement the same:
وأُنهي كُلّ بلاغ بنفس الطريقة:
"If nobody told you they loved you today,
" اذا لم يُخبرك أحد أنه يًحبك اليوم،
you remember I do,
فتذكر أنني أحبك،
and I always will."
وسأظل أحبك"
Ashley's words
كلمات آشلي
of "Miss, Miss,
" آنستي، آنستي
this is not a school,"
هذه ليست مدرسة."
is forever etched in my mind.
ستظل عالقة في ذهني إلى الأبد.
If we are truly going to make real progress
إذا كنا سنُحرز تقدّما
in addressing poverty,
في معالجة قضية الفقر،
then we have to make sure
يجب علينا أن نتحقق
that every school that serves children in poverty
من أنّ كل مدرسة يلتحق بها الفقراء
is a real school,
هي حقّا مدرسة،
a school, a school --
مدرسة، مدرسة --
(Applause) --
(تصفيق) --
a school that provides them with knowledge
مدرسة تُوفّر لهم المعرفة
and mental training to navigate the world around them.
والتدريب الذهني للإبحار في العالم حولهم.
I do not know all the answers,
أنا لا أعرف كلّ الأجوبة
but what I do know is for those of us who are privileged
ولكن ما أعرفه هو أن أولائك المتميزين
and have the responsibility of leading a school that serves children in poverty,
والذين يتمتعون بمسؤولية القيادة بمدرسة يلتحق بها الفقراء،
we must truly lead,
فإن علينا حقا أن نمارس دور القيادة،
and when we are faced with unbelievable challenges,
وعندما تواجهنا مجموعة من التحديات الصعبة ،
we must stop and ask ourselves, "So what. Now what?
ينبغي أن نقف ونسأل انفسنا، " وإن يكن؟! أين المفر؟!
What are we going to do about it?"
ماذا سنفعل بخصوص هذا؟"
And as we lead,
ونحن نقوم بالقيادة
we must never forget
يجب أن لا ننسى أبدا
that every single one of our students
بأن كل تلميذ من تلامذتنا
is just a child,
هو مجرّد طفل،
often scared by what the world tells them they should be,
يخاف دائما ممّا يُخبره العالم كيف ينبغي أن يكون،
and no matter what the rest of the world tells them they should be,
ومهما أخبره العالم عن
we should always provide them with hope,
يجب أن نُزوّدهم دائما بالأمل،
our undivided attention,
اهتمامنا الكامل،
unwavering belief in their potential,
اقتناعنا التام بإمكانيّاتهم،
consistent expectations,
الآمال المستمرّة
and we must tell them often,
ويجب أن نّخبرهم دائما،
if nobody told them they loved them today,
إذا لم يُخبرهم أحد بأنه يّحبّهم اليوم،
remember we do, and we always will.
فليتذكروا بأننا نُحبهم، وسنظلّ نُحبّهم
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you, Jesus.
شكرا، يسوع.